{
  "reference_number": "10887",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "No time is short . before climate change is catastrophic. We need to set a target, form a plan to reach the target, stick to the plan. If\n\n we don't act now and set a meaningful target,it will be too late. The only way it should be revised is to make the changes sooner."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Its often easier to break targets into smaller targets. I would like assurances that all Parties will stick to the plan. NZ could be a leader\n\n in the Southern Hemsphere."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Climate change affects us all. Every New Zealander, our Pacific neighbours, the World population. The emissions budget should be\n part of a long term plan to stabilise climate change. There will be a need for us all to change behaviour, some industries and\n individuals will need to change more. They should be supported through these changes long term. All Political Parties should agree\n\n with and stick to the planned budget. There should be no adjustments or changes for short term popularism."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "No This is a long term plan, as stated above change will be hard and no doubt the government will be under pressure to respond to\n\nthose most effected. If industry and business are aware of the possibility of moveable targets they are much less likely to fully apply\nthemselves to achieving the target in the first place"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "especially the statement about being transparent and predictable while undertaking its functions."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Goal setting should always include TIMELY !"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "NZ is so blessed with renewable energy sources. Could the government support solar panels in selected state\nhouses/schools/hospitals. Initially in sunny regions eg Hawkes Bay /Nelson any extra power going to community batteries. Could you\n\nconsider a Nationalised renewable electricity company with the option of individuals producing more power than they need donating\nit to their local community for use in schools/hospitals/resthomes etc ie incentives to get the local community thinking about how\ntheir actions can positively impact others in their neighbourhood Promote electric transport, more charging points"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "It's important that an independent scientific climate commission sets the targets. As previously stated tackling climate change needs\nto a longterm plan not subject to changing political moods"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Would love to see a \"science communicator\"role in their (? even an intern) as need to make the goals and plan easy to understand\n\nand get behind"
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Its part of the big picture"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "lets work together"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "To get all NZers behind the Goals they need to understand how emissions cause climate change. More public education/information\n\nis needed."
    }
  ]
}
